Um So you don't need any tools today. It's
just gonna be us and our bodies and we're gonna
flow a little bit through the whole body. We'll
hit most of your systems today. Um And um
maybe we can really kind of focus on getting some
of that rotation back and, and also I think
what we'll do today is also gonna support a startle
reflex as well, which can all be protective response
. So we've got, we've got a good,
I've got a good little flow plan today. So
let's start standing, sorry, love bug. I'm
sorry. OK. So let's start standing and since
we are standing hit with distance apart, mark this
part and we're gonna do a full body rotation to
do our assessment to start with. And of course
, if you want to do any of the others
feel free but have this spot mark so that,
you know, you can come back to it.
I like to point my fingers or do uh both
palms together and you just wanna do that full body
rotation kind of getting that marker of where you're at
where you're at today. And let's see if we
can we're on, I'm not going to assess after
every drill today. This is a flow. So
we'll only be assessing intermittently if at any point you
want to reassess something that we've done by all means
, you know, please do that. And so
we are gonna stay in this hip with distance apart
. This fine is gonna stay straight and we're going
to rotate the hips in a circle, almost creating
this hour glass figure with our shoulders and our hips
rotating the pelvis. Good. We're doing four in
each direction. So last one good and then let's
reverse. So from the side, your shoulders go
in opposition of your hips, straight spine kind of
pushing the hips forward, shoulders back. Last one
good, we'll come back to standing next, interlace
your hands behind your head. Shoulders in the periphery
, sit up nice and tall and give me a
little tuck of the chin and then lift through the
crown of the head. So you're really reaching an
opposition, be feel grounded on the mat, crown
of the head lengthens up. We're going to flex
over to the left and rotate flex and rotate.
Flex, rotate and then unwind and come all the
way up. Let's go to the other side.
We flex a little rotate down, flex, rotate
, flex, rotate, let's come up and unwind
good. Now, release the right arm down,
left arm up and we're gonna do something kind of
similar this time, we're going to flex and open
up to the ceiling, flex, open, flex
, open, unwind and switch. So we rotate
, rotate and rotate and unwind. Good. Now
, give your low back a little bit of sensory
stimulus here, we're gonna start with our spine.
We're gonna start mobilizing and working with this thoracic spine
. And I think it's a good idea to give
yourself a little bit of sensory stimulus before we move
into anything lateral or anything in the thoracic. So
we're going to, if you have the opportunity,
you can back yourself up against a wall, you
don't have to. But the idea would be that
the hips stay still. They are not mobile.
OK. So either way you go through this,
just keep that in mind. So feed or hip
with distance apart, you're gonna laterally glide over to
the right. Selects the spine, rotate the shoulder
down, keeping the hips where they are sway over
to the side. We're gonna rotate open laterally flex
and then glide back into place. Let's go the
opposite way. So we glide flex, rotate,
sweep it around, then we un rotate or rotate
flex and then come back to neutral. Let's do
that one more time flex or glide flex, rotate
, sway around and doesn't have to be deep.
Remember, we're trying to keep our hips pinned up
against the wall. Last time on their side,
glide flex rotate, sweep it around and then come
back up and unwind. Good. Let's work a
little bit through some scapular mobility. So the arm
will extend out just directly in front of you.
Move it out to about a 45 degree angle.
And we're gonna begin by lifting the scapula up,
pulling it back, dropping it down, reaching it
forward, up, back down forward. Good start
to round that movement out, reach up and back
. I'd like to envision sort of a locomotive kind
of action in my shoulder here, Just the shoulder
is moving. Let's reverse that, pull it back
, lift it up, reach it forward, good
down, back up forward. So to just round
it up but two more, the last one and
release other side arm extends out to 45. We
lift up, pull back decom compress down and reach
so up, back down out good. Just start
rounding it out the more comfortable you get with it
can always keep the movement separate as you need to
last one and reverse. So we're reaching forward,
we're gonna pull it down and back and up.
Good. Beautiful. That looks really nice y'all last
two and one watch for any tension, you start
to feel any tension on the other side of the
body like, oh you're starting to grip on the
other side. That's gonna be an indication that there's
too much mobility happening. So just always being aware
of what the other side is doing when one side
is moving. So we're gonna mobilize through the ankles
and through the feet here by rolling onto one side
so that both soles of the feet uh are facing
the wall and then we roll through to the other
edge of the foot. Now, both soles of
the feet are reaching the others touching the other side
. So we just rolling through the ankle, exposing
the soles of the feet to the other side.
Good feeling that roll onto the sides, the full
foot placement and then rolling through but not pushing into
any pain or discomfort here. Good, breathing nice
and gently, we'll go a couple more each way
. Good. Last one and one beautiful shape that
out a little bit. And then let's reassess from
here before we go on to the mountain. Let's
see how we're doing, making sure that before we
go on any further. If there's any drills that
you need to do before we move to the map
to take your rotation up. If you have a
high reward, pay up that you do, then
go ahead and do that and you can meet me
on the mat in a comfortable seated position. So
we're gonna work on a little bit. Uh Let
me see. Could you please call aside, you're
rotating? Oh, sorry about that, Vicky.
I'm sorry, y'all, I don't have the notes
are kind of far away. So at any point
, if you have any questions or you, if
I can do anything for you, please just go
on and put your speaker on if you have any
questions, I would, you won't be bothering me
or interrupting me at all. So let's come to
a seated position. We're gonna work on some spinal
mobility that thoracic spine once again. So you can
anchor your palms here on your knees and give your
sternum a little bit of sensory stimulus here because we
do use it as a cue when we move our
thoracic spine and anterior posterior position. Good. So
we are going to lengthen the spine, nice and
tall, gentle pull back of the chin and then
we're gonna lift the sternum up on a diagonal and
then pull it back, the shoulders stay fixed as
the spine glides back and forth, anchoring the shoulders
over the hips, gentle glide of the spine.
Good. Let's include our breath. Now. So
on the inhale, the sternum reaches up and on
the exhale, we pull the spine back. So
inhale, lift, exhale, pull good. Let's
add the eyes here. Inhale, the eyes go
up to the eyebrows, just the eyes are moving
as we pull the spine back, the gaze drops
to the cheek. So inhale, eyes lift to
the brow, exhale, we pull back and the
gaze drops to the cheeks two more good. Last
one. And now we're gonna end in our inhale
, pushing the sternum forward and holding the gaze up
to the eyebrows in this fixed position for about 10
seconds. Just relax and breathe into this fixed position
. 4321 and release. So from here, we're
going to do a vertical smooth pursuit with the thumb
. So you've got your thumb in a comfortable position
out in front of your nose, maybe about 10
to 12 inches. We're gonna trace the, uh
, the thumb, the gaze goes up, we're
gonna shut the eye and bring the thumb back to
neutral. Open, track it up, just the
eyes are moving. So don't go too high,
shut the eyes back to neutral. Good. Few
more times looking up, tracking that gaze shut back
to neutral. Two more last one. Good.
Now we're gonna do a lateral glide from side to
side with that same thoracic spine good just being mindful
here. If the opposite hip begins to lift or
just being really mindful of the, of the movement
here in general, just don't pushing it too far
. Remember, you don't have to have a large
movement just a little bit. We want to be
precise. Let's do two more either way. Good
. Last one and one and let's come back to
center. The next vision drill that we're gonna do
today is near far. So you can bring your
thumb back up in front of you, maybe even
a little closer this time, about six inches away
from the nose. And then you're gonna choose an
object, something that you can make contact with maybe
about 8 to 10 ft away. So we'll look
at our thumb, look away, look far,
come back to the thumb and find your gaze fixed
on something far and bring it back. We're far
near far, near two more. Go ahead and
release that and kind of shake that out or if
you need to, you can always do a visual
reset here. If one of those drills felt like
it was pushing just a little bit. OK.
So here we are going to, I want you
to find your far away focus that you just used
in that near far drill. I want you to
fix your gaze upon it and begin to circle the
thoracic spine. So we're combining the posterior anterior with
the lateral good and let's use our breath as we
exhale the spine rounds back and as we put a
shit forward, we inhale good back, inhale,
lift, exhale, pull the spine back, beautiful
one more, holding that gaze and let's reverse,
exhale, pull back and lift on the inhale.
But sinking our breath with our movement. Last one
and coming back to center, release the right arm
down by your side and we are going to reach
the hand out laterally, flex the head in the
opposite direction. And with the left hand, we're
gonna start at the ox aut around the back and
we're going to run three fingers down the S C
M into the collarbone good just going from the back
of the neck around that ropy next mus neck muscle
and into the collarbone. Good. Let's do that
two more times says the accessory nerve that runs through
that S C M and we're gonna do a little
accessory nerve glide nerve flossing here. So this right
arm is not, is now going to comp decompress
through the show through the scapula. So you're really
gonna press the scapula down, even pulling it back
towards the spine gently here, the fingertips can touch
or the palm can be facing the floor, pull
the chin back in that lateral refle uh lateral flexion
and then like a chicken, there's a posterior anterior
glide of the cervical spine good, just giving that
accessory nerve a little bit of a glide and two
and one, hold the head back and pump the
scapula up and down. We're looking for about a
three out of 10 of intensity. So try not
to get too straining with it. Last two,
last one good and release. Let's go to the
other side. So the left palm goes out,
fingertips are just reaching out for the floor flex the
neck away. And with your three fingers to come
back from the neck cross that Roy muscle into the
collarbone good, starting at like just below the occiput
, make sure you're breathing into a relaxed belly good
. And now we have our head flexed away.
I want you to press the shoulder blade down and
then pull it back towards the spine. Good.
Now, pull the chin back in that lateral,
lateral flexion and then we lift posterior anterior glide a
little bit of a chicken ball. Good. Keeping
that scapula decompressed too and one and release there good
. So from here, we're gonna move into a
shin box position, one of your legs will be
forward. I wanna hit the wall. So I'm
just gonna screw it up slightly here. Now,
you can use your hands for assistance here or you
can hold them up. But what we're gonna do
is move from shin box to shin box. Ok
? So both feet make contact and we're around and
then we go back the other way. One thing
that can happen here too, sometimes you can really
start traveling in the room. Actually, it was
kind of scooting around. So just try and always
come back to the place where we start and come
back. I am totally traveling as I say that
um and you can use your palms on the floor
for guidance. If that feels too heavy in the
hips, just pop your hands behind you. And
that will help you keep the spine from flexing too
much in this and for you getting too in more
of like rounded spine. We don't wanna do that
. We wanna keep the spine lifted as we work
through these hips good. We'll do this two more
times and the last one good coming back to center
and we are gonna pop back up to standing and
shake it out. A little bit. We are
gonna finish with some coordination and some activation for our
cerebellum. So what I want you to do is
bring your hands up, bring your fingers up me
, get closer so you can see me. Ok
? What this is gonna look like is pointer,
middle fourth, pinky, pinky fourth, middle pointer
pointer, middle fourth, pinky, pinky fourth,
middle pointer. Good. Can we speed that up
? Good. Can you shut your eyes? Uh
just breathing into a relaxed belly. Noticing if one
hand, one finger is having a harder time?
Ok. Let's do one more round. Oh and
shake that out. Good. And then let's reassess
that. How's everybody doing after that cerebellum drill?
Are we good? Oh No, Lizzie. No
, do if that got you because it can be
activating just to another high reward payoff drill. Bring
yourself back and let's go through some of that thoracic
mobilization now that we're standing so feed our hip with
distance apart and we're gonna begin that rounding circling the
rib cage around the pelvis. Remember the shoulders are
fixed but inhale, exhale. Now this time with
the eyes, we're gonna move them in a circle
. So we're gonna, the, the eyes are
gonna follow the spine so they're gonna track up or
to the side around and up. Good. You
can maybe trace something in your room in front of
you that imaginary line and reverse. So stay with
the breath, adding the eyes if that's too much
. You can shut the eyes and relax. Let's
step it out a little bit further here and we're
gonna rotate and palpate the palpate the rib cage and
the back as we move our arms around, just
getting a little bit more support and accessing our rotation
. Go ahead last two and one and one and
we'll come back to standing. We're gonna move on
to some neck proprioceptive work by doing some neck bow
ties, which will start as bow ties with sharp
corners. And then just like we did with our
shoulder mobility, we're gonna just start rounding that out
the whole time, the nose and the face stay
forward. So, and I get closer so that
you can see my face so the nose will track
to the top right corner and down, up the
45 to the left and down. Watch your rotation
here. It's very easy for the head to want
to rotate so that you get more range of motion
, but it's not about how far we go.
It's about the precision. Just start rounding it out
. Beautiful. Last two, last one, come
to center and reverse. Uh, just going straight
into that infinity. The neck beautiful last two,
last one back to neutral. And let's reassess our
range of motion from here. How are we doing
? Good. Well, I see some good yawning
. So I'm feeling good about that. That's awesome
. Um The last thing that we, um,
are going to do today is, um, the
last thing that we are gonna do today is,
hm, I think we're kind of done. Actually
. I don't have anything back here. I thought
I had one more thing. I've got something on
my mind that keeps running through, but as long
as we're all feeling good, I think that might
be a good place to stop. How are we
all feeling, any thoughts or questions about what we
just did, Maria? Are you doing better now
? Awesome. Awesome. And the short and sweet
today, I have a question. Sure. When
I do, well, a lot of that for
a lot of that, um, like I feel
nauseous, I always feel nausea. I don't always
feel nauseous when I do it. I instantly feel
nauseous. Um, but when I do my,
um, like the assessments, they're always neutral,
they're not negative. Um, and especially nauseous if
it's like a part of my body, like my
right shoulder or my right foot that I've injured before
. Um, so I just kind of judge it
and, like, do it and then maybe do
a high, like, step out and do a
high payoff drill. But is that what I should
be doing if I can? Not, just because
I think I judge it whether it's one of the
ones I should push through or not because I,
the eyes, I can't push through yet. But
, um, the other parts, yeah, I
would not push through nausea. I remember the concept
of what we do, we get better at.
So we wouldn't want to push through pain, we
wouldn't wanna push through nausea. And so are you
, does that happen only on the right side where
there's injury or is that also happening as you go
through the left side as well? It happens,
um, with, well, mostly the right side
because all the injuries have been the right side.
Um, But it can happen like, um when
you're, when you're just talking like through the eye
drills because I can't, the eye drills totally set
me off. But when, if I'm just listening
to you doing them, um it at the beginning
of this class, it used to make me nauseous
and now I like can tell that I'm getting better
that I could listen to you doing them. Sometimes
I can even watch. Um So I feel like
, like I'm slowly working there, I can't do
them well, especially with contact thing because I'm on
a vision. But um but yeah, no,
the nausea can just be even hearing you talk about
like doing something with some part of the body that
obviously makes my body uncomfortable. Ok. Here's a
couple of things I would suggest as you're working with
the right side, I would treat the right side
and the left side, completely independent of each other
. And on the right side really be so small
and maybe even visualize it instead of doing the drill
at all, try and visualize the drill and see
if that would reassess positively because I, I y'all
would be surprised at how big of a high reward
you can get in a drill just by visualizing it
. So I would start there. And another thing
that I would do is, you know, if
the left side has its full range of motion and
say we're doing the scapula work and that's like feeling
really good. But on the right side, stop
and visualize and then reassess. Um and on the
vision stuff, you if if you are in a
visual reset like this and I'm describing vision work that
is um prompting nausea. Um No, like that's
getting better at the beginning of the course, there
were certain things that I can't mm mm like I
couldn't do anything vision but now like, yeah,
I can listen to the vision stuff. Um and
I can watch now I can watch now some of
it being done. I just um not all of
it. Sometimes I get nauseous but I just know
like anything where it's been any injury part of my
body, I instantly get nauseous when you even bring
up like um even with the like the scapula for
the left side, even though it's my right side
that I had reconstructive surgery on like, you know
, it's just I wonder what it would be like
if you laid down and visualized it. Oh,
I'm gonna try that. That's, I think because
laying down is going to take stimulus away. Yeah
. No, that's a good idea. I like
that. I would try that. Try that and
let me know how that goes. I'd be interested
to hear that. Ok, because, yeah,
like, it's hard because I don't want to,
like, not come to the class. I mean
, I'm going to come to the class but,
like, then a lot of times I'm just OK
. Should I do it? Should I not if
I'm instantly nauseous? Yeah. No, instantly,
no, I reward and then take it down,
take it down, take it down, take it
all the way down to the, like I said
, laying down and visualization. OK. Thank you
. Yeah, you're welcome. Thank you. Uh
I was gonna say um so all of this vision
respiration and vestibular training, all three of those I
had to start out like little baby steps, big
lessons for me in minimum effective dose. And you've
already had some experience Janine in, in getting better
and making progress. So you can see that those
, you know, it doesn't matter how big your
step is, those baby steps will get you there
. It is. That's a good point. I
mean, honestly, because like even when we're talking
about thoracic glides and like I've been doing thoracic glides
my whole life basically, even before N si so
, you know, I the mechanics of it like
you don't right now, it probably doesn't even look
like my spine's moving very much. It's just a
little right. And then eventually you get more range
of motion as you do it with precision. But
it doesn't have to be large at all. And
it's like that with any of the drills. Right
. See, so I'm like circling my rib cage
around my pelvis now. But it can be so
small, it can just be so small it with
any of the drills and you can honestly visualization is
such a strong tool. I have a question.
Mhm We do the bow tie infinity with and show
me the head position. So your head position is
forward and just my nose is the tool. Imagine
if you had a marker, a crayon, a
pen, whatever you're gonna do and that's gonna trace
with the nose. So the nose goes up,
down, across and down. So there can be
, there can be a wanting to like see how
I'm like actually rotating my neck. My nose is
kind of going off to the side. That's what
we really want to be mindful of is that neck
rotation. So when I'm doing it, OK.
Thank you. Yeah, you're welcome, Cynthia,
you mentioned um laying down and I, I've,
I've been wanting to try some of that and,
and to lay down, but I realized that I
, I don't know how to um test laying down
. Yeah. And it, this thing with my
arm doesn't work. It like it doesn't, I
don't feel anything and if I was gonna lay down
and reas and assess it might look something like this
, I wanna make sure you can see me,
ok, your feet can be up like this or
they can be out whatever is the most comfortable for
your spine to be in. If I was gonna
do some of the vision drills or even the scapula
stuff laying down, I would probably have my feet
planted on the floor instead of them being out like
this because that low spine, if, if you're
not in a neutral pelvis position, that low spine
can then um, maybe have a poor outcome.
But so you're saying, can you internally externally rotate
the shoulder? Yeah. Ok. So that would
be one, you could still do a abduction of
the, of the shoulder. You could also do
neck rotation. What else could you do down here
? Hm. I think that seems to be it
. Oh, you could also assess what it's like
to have your arms overhead. I have a shoulder
injury on the right side. You could assess what
it's like to have your shoulders overhead. You could
do this one. Could you rotate your spine by
dropping your knees side to side? Well, this
would be more windshield wiper of the hips. Is
this what you mean? I was just wondering if
that's more like spinal rotation. I don't think this
is because this movement here. It, it is
happening a little bit in the low spine, but
a lot more is happening in my hips. I
would think more of either the abduction, abduction,
internal external rotation, neck trying to think what,
what confused me is that, um, you know
, especially with my arm. When I'm standing up
, I can't really get it all the way down
and sometimes I can, I get a high payoff
and it'll come down when I'm laying down, everything's
good. Even my, you know, and I
have a lot of problem with my neck and when
I'm laying down and I turn, I hardly feel
anything. It might be that laying down is the
way that you should be doing some of the drills
. If you're assessing better on the floor, then
standing, then I think you might want to take
more things down to the floor. Ok. Yeah
, because I deal with a lot of pain with
my neck, you know, just even turning my
neck, you know, it's doing this, it's
really painful and I'm like letting it be painful.
No, don't do that and assessing and assessing that
way. Oh, well, but there have been
times when it really lessened, you know, but
I, I shouldn't be going to that pain place
. Huh? No, no. Just like I
was saying before, like, what we do we
get better at and what's happening is when the pain
is, um, triggered as the neural pathway that's
carved and then it's like, OK, that gets
triggered. I'm in pain and we keep using that
pathway, you're just, you're just making it a
better, easier pathway to get through because you're laying
more myelin down around the pathway, right? Like
that myelin is if you think of a wire,
right? And then the pathway of the neurons is
the wire and it's just like um and then you
have the plastic around the wire, the myelin is
what is going around that, those, that neural
network and it's just getting stronger, getting stronger,
getting every time you push through, it'd be the
same for uh Janine. If she was to push
through nausea, it'd be like, oh trigger the
nausea. Oh She, she likes that. Let's
just easy. It'd be easier to just trigger the
nausea, trigger the nausea, trigger the pain because
it gets to be a more well worn path because
it gets myelinated. So when you're not feeling pain
, what are you assessing when you do the,
the uh, reset the, uh, checking it
out? I've gotta keep forgetting that word. Well
, you could as, I mean, so you
assessing if it's not pain or not feeling pain or
is there anything that you do that is not painful
? An assessment that you do that doesn't cause you
pain. Well, even when I do this,
you know this, I only go to a place
where it, it hurts. Ok. Ok.
I know. I, so all of these things
, I'm assess. I'm in assessing pain is what
I'm doing. Yeah. Yeah. Ok. So
a couple of things that you could reassess would be
, your vocal tone could be, handwriting could be
balance. Like, do you know what your balance
is like to stand on one leg for 30 seconds
or to stand with the feet together or even to
put one in front of the other? And that's
hard. That's kind of hard. Yeah. Start
playing with one of those. Ok. Wow.
I guess it took me a long time to figure
this out. I hope I didn't go backwards.
No, you're not, you're catching it and,
uh, being aware of it, it's gonna be
ok, it's gonna be ok. Someone asked,
um, what does yawning mean? Yawning is a
beautiful release of the body and I wanna say now
and Cynthia, I wouldn't, I wouldn't worry so
much about, you know, paint, like doing
things and, and taking a step back. I
mean, the bottom line is that it took us
years, some of us, well, me personally
, 68 years to get to this point. Um
, a, a lot of things happening in that
time. It, you know, this has been
a, we've all had a lifetime of, of
injuries and, and various other issues in our bodies
. So it's not gonna, it doesn't just get
better overnight. It doesn't just go away. You
have to reprogram your, your, your body and
your mind and your nervous system. And, and
it's a process but it's, it can be fun
if you just, if you look at it and
approach it with more, more curiosity, it,
it's not like I don't think of it as fixing
myself. I, I, I look at it
more as like, hm. Ok. What's it
doing now? How is it reacting to this?
Ok. You didn't like this. Let's try this
. Um, you know, and with without,
without judging or, or moving into pain. That's
and this, this has been a big lesson for
me. I did not learn this overnight. So
and you can reassess your handwriting as you go through
this, you can keep a pen and paper next
to you. See what it's like to say there
are certain letters or numbers that I just don't,
I always feel like, oh man, that looks
so bad. Like I can't write a cursive G
very well or something, right? And so what
does it look like as I move through this work
to try my cursive G? Yeah, I literally
anything can be a reassessment or you don't want to
go to pain. You don't wanna be reassessing pain
like oh, is that better? Less pain or
more pain? Well, you can, you ok
, I'm hearing a couple different things because like if
I show up with say maybe say I slept a
little bit wrong on my neck and I don't,
I'm not someone who normally feels pain in my neck
but it feels like, oh, there's a little
bit of a trick here. I might assess that
because I'm not usually in pain, but if I'm
doing something that always is causing pain and then I'm
continuing to assess that and I'm always just going to
, ok, let me just rotate till I find
pain. We're rotating till we find that, um
, that sort of, uh, oh, what's
the word? Like the place that gets a little
bit? Um oh, what's the word I'm looking
for? Like a little bit stuck, you know
, but not pain. If this were to cause
me pain, I would not be reassessing and assessing
it. What's the word? Because you're gonna hit
a place in your rotation where you've hit your edge
but not if the edge causes pain when I'm realizing
that I've just been in, in pain. I
, and I would say this my mo my mother
and the doctors would tell my mother, I've never
seen anybody handle the pain like you do. You
have a strong, you know, and I,
and I think I do the same thing. I
just ignore pain or work through it or whatever.
I, for a long time, it's like a
old pattern. So this is really different for me
to think about this, this way. Yeah.
Yeah. You're welcome. I'm gonna tell you,
I'm gonna bring up one other thing um for pain
to just kind of tell you about because pain in
general is, is an output of a nervous system
that is under too much stress, right? From
a, from a neurological perspective, pain is an
output of your brain trying to get you to change
your behavior. When we have an acute injury,
there's pain and there's an action signal, right?
Something is wrong and you need to do something about
it. So like if we cut ourselves or burn
ourselves, we experience that pain. So we don't
go back to burning or cutting ourselves, right?
Like if you think about the burners on the stove
and you accidentally touch it, oh, I felt
that pain, right. I'm not gonna do that
again. It's the same thing with the signal in
your body because you don't want to keep doing the
pain. So sometimes there can be a biomechanical issue
, like maybe there's tissue damage or o osteoarthritis in
the joint. However, when you get into those
long term chronic injuries, there's a lot of evidence
that shows that like we all have this degeneration,
meniscus tears in our knee arthritis in our joints and
it's normal that our bodies wear out over time and
wear down over time. But we don't all experience
that same amount of pain. And that's because some
of us are experiencing less stress on a daily basis
. And when we have less stress, these other
biomechanical issues are not gonna be as threatening. Our
brain isn't gonna be as worried about it. And
pain is a really great tool when there's just too
much stress and when we're in pain, we do
less, we interact less with the world. We
take smaller steps, we work out less or maybe
not as intense at all. And so we just
really wanna be careful about like the stress level and
the pain level and trying to find the thread um
, between these two, like, um, like
, think of someone who has low back pain and
also hates their job. Right. There's actually a
huge correlation between these two things. A lot of
people who hate their jobs also have, um,
low back pain. So if you are in that
pain and theoretically, you do less interact with the
world less if the job is stressful and your low
back already hurts and then you throw your back out
, then you don't have to go to work at
all. You stay in bed, you rest and
your brain has kept you safe because you threw your
back out. Right? You push through the person
pushes through the pain enough to actually injure themselves in
their back. And then what happens? Well,
it probably pain is gonna stop at some point because
you're not gonna have to go to work to the
job that you hate, that's causing the stress that's
causing the pain. How does that feel? Yeah
. It, yeah, it, it seems like
I've heard it. I don't, I think in
this class too that, uh, Melanie was saying
something about studies that show that you, you know
, people have deteriorated, you know, arthritis in
their back and they do the MRI S and half
of those people do not feel pain and the other
half feel pain. It did. So it's not
, it's not, I I'm, you know,
this is new to hear that. So, yeah
, I actually have stenosis in one of my uh
lower vertebra S L five S one, something like
that really low. I never feel that pain,
like never. And stenosis is a literally choking out
of the nerve in the vertebra. I have a
friend who has the exact same thing and he is
always in pain. He has terrible O CD.
He's very activated all the time and he feels his
back and I have the exact same thing. I
never feel my spine. Never. It's very rare
if I do. I'm like, oh shoot,
I'm stressed. What's going on here. I just
felt my back. Well, and I think we
live in a, we live in a culture.
Um I was, I was always known for having
a, a very high pain tolerance and for years
, um I wore it like a badge. Yeah
, me too. You know. Um And the
, the bottom line is that what I was,
what I was doing all of this time was simply
, you know, overriding what my body was trying
to tell me your body's talking to you. I
, I have personally found that the in Interception meditations
on the site have been very helpful for me because
I, I hear my body but I can't,
I would hear it but I would just keep,
I would just ignore it, push it down,
push it down, ignore it. Keep going.
I be in acceptance me interception interception cept when,
uh, uh, well, she's there occasionally.
Those are done on Sundays, but I think Jennifer
, are there not some recordings on the, there's
gonna be audio recordings on the site where you can
find that, that where you can find that meditation
. And I would, I would lean into some
stress processing also. Like, I don't know what
your emotional processing is like, but I would lean
into that. I would really look into that.
Yeah, because sometimes you just can't drill your way
out of pain like you, it's, sometimes it's
not gonna be a drill that's gonna get you out
of pain. Sometimes it's gonna be emotional. Yeah
, I do a lot of emotional work, you
know, uh, about, since we, you
know, I've been doing it for years and I
cry easily, you know, I can, I
can release a lot of stuff that way. But
, but, you know, so there's a lot
of emotional things going on with me but, but
I've come a long way too, you know,
I'm, it's like I'm here. Right. Yeah
. Absolutely. I mean, you know, it's
a journey like Susan said, like, we've been
, just been at it for years. I mean
, I'm 74. I just, you know,
a lot of years there. Yeah. Yeah,
I think, yeah, when you think how long
it's been that you've been doing something that's gotten you
to hear, it's not just gonna be like,
oh, I've got some tools now, I've got
these drills and it's gonna be a shorter, it
could be, you know, it's gonna take some
space as well. It's like that's the hard thing
about uh trauma and stories and narrative is that like
it happens like that, but it don't go away
like that. So it's just, there's all these
layers, just layers and layers and layers and layers
, just peel, peeling back the onion, you
know, totally and taking things really slow, really
slow exercises, small and precise like, yeah,
well, I can't get that in my head.
I wanna like go to the max, you know
that when you used to doing that right back to
that net work is like, oh no, I'm
gonna do this. I am gonna do this even
if the pathway to do it is through pain.
So that push, push, push, which once
again is always rewarded by society. You know,
the the the overperforming overdo is always rewarded and but
it doesn't reward ourselves. Who does that? Reward
it? It's a heavy price. Got you and
women particularly. I mean, we've carried a lot
, we carry a lot. We've been driving for
hard, hard and fast for a long, long
time and a lot, uh, you know,
well, this is now gonna speak to rest and
slowing down, which can also feel really threatening when
you're not used to doing that. So if,
if that, if you are one of those over
drivers just doing, doing, doing, doing,
doing, doing, doing, doing, try and
slow the, doing down, you know, if
you're like, I always tell my clients like,
if you're making a stew and you've got all these
vegetables that you need to wash, you know,
get the potato. It's nice and slow. Let
the water run over your hands. Feel the potato
. OK. Next boom. Get those carrots that
the eyes, feel the carrot, feel the water
. You know what I'm saying? Like really just
slowing little tiny things down because when we want to
make change, we don't have to go to the
max and expect that like, oh, it's,
it's through there. If I push hard enough.
Like if you think of throwing a pebble into a
pond into a lake, the tiniest pebble is gonna
make a ripple in the water. You don't have
to get the massive stone to create the change in
that water. It's tiny. Wow, you're really
speaking to me, you're really speaking to me.
I mean, I'm the fastest dishwasher. I'm the
fastest this, you know, uh and that's just
like how my whole life has been because we just
everything's go, go, go and, and go
faster, faster, faster, run, hurry up
, hurry up and then hurry up and then wait
, hurry up and wait. We do that so
much. And, and I found that even just
little things like I, I noticed when I,
you know, after I shower because I have dry
skin and I, and I put lotion on it
and I would just, I'd get out and like
in a hurry trying to get it all on and
, and, and move on. And one day
when I got out of the shower, I was
, I started to put lotion on and I just
, and just it came into my head how my
massage therapist touches my skin so lovingly and I thought
, why the hell am I not doing that for
me? And I started trying to just slow that
down, you know, oh and, and you
know, you just even just that sensory stimulus of
, of, you know, and, and show
your body some love which I was have not done
in a, in a long time. Um just
, you know, reacquainting yourself and, and falling
back in love with yourself, fall in love yourself
preaching Susan that is beautiful. I just love that
so much sensory stimulus. Uh Cynthia might be a
really good idea for your neck or the places where
you do feel pain, find something that you like
the feel of. Some ladies use a jade roller
. You could get a dry brush, you could
use uh any side of a fork, right?
The, the back side of the fork is gonna
be cool and smooth or you could use the,
the tongs tis, what are those things called?
Just run, you know, find the stimulus that
feels good for you. Whether that's a silk cloth
or a cotton cloth or, you know, when
you take a shower, shut your eyes and start
feeling the water. Where is the water running over
my body right now? Where is that? You
know, and just start cultivating that relationship with your
exteroceptive system, that sensory stimulus. And then also
like Susan, getting back to that interoceptive system and
slowing things down and instead of feeling like I'm gonna
get a reward for how fast I go, find
a reward for how slow you go. Right.
There you go. Honestly, like, and I
, and celebrating wins, celebrating the slowness. And
I mean, I'm someone who, when I,
when I say set a goal or something I'm moving
towards, I get a literal present like I am
treating myself to something, whatever that is, you
know, it's like, OK, I'm gonna reach
this point and then what or hey, I'm halfway
there. What, what, how can I treat
myself? Look how good I've come. How good
can I be to myself? You know? Mhm
Thank you so much. You're welcome. You're welcome
beginning. Yes. Yeah. And let's start working
on those reassessments and finding you something. Ok.
Balance, balance sounds like it might be a good
idea. Yeah, I got a high payoff with
doing those kind of drills too with closing your eyes
and put, you know, and it's real.
It's not easy for me. Great, great.
Thank you, Brenda. Thank you. Thanks y'all
. It was really good to see you. Thank
you so much for the engagement. Yeah, you're
so inspiring all of you. Thank you so much
. Y'all too. Y'all are also very inspiring.
So thank you. Thank you. Bye.